Minna Citron Papers
Minna Citron Papers
1932-2014
Citron, Minna, 1896-1991.
3.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, 1946-1965; typescript essays; exhibition catalogs, invitations, and posters; photographs of Minna Citron and her work; newspaper clippings; and publicity
149451
Biographical History
Minna Citron (1896-1991) was an American painter and printmaker.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Minna Citron Papers encompasses the correspondence, artwork, writings and memorabilia of the American painter and graphic artist (1896-1991). Although revealing little of her personal life, the collection documents Citron's artistic career from the 1930s through the mid-sixties.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing business letters, a few from the 1940s followed by a gap during the 1950s. Resuming in 1961 and continuing through 1965, the Correspondence focuses on Minna Citron's associations with art galleries (Ferdinand Roten Galleries, Inc., Aspen Art Gallery), educational institutions (Elmira College), museums (Whitney Museum of American Art, Roanoke Fine Arts Center), professional organizations (American Color Print Society, American Federation of Arts) and public libraries which sponsored her lectures or held exhibitions of her work.
Artwork includes an original etching for a bookplate, a partial inventory of Minna Citron's paintings and graphics, and black-and-white photographs of her work. Arranged by title, Writings feature manuscript essays and speeches as well as two articles, "Communication Between Spectator and Artist" (College Art Journal, Winter 1955), and: "The Uncharted Course" (Impression, Fall 1958).
Memorabilia contains awards, personal photographs, printed material, publicity, and reviews and comments about Minna Citron's work. Printed material includes clippings (1932-1965), exhibition catalogs (1930s-1960s) and posters for Minna Citron's one-woman and group shows.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type of material.
Related Material
See also the Aaron Bohrod Papers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Citron, Minna, 1896-1991.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Engravers -- United States.; Engraving -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century -- United States.; Printmakers -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Women painters -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Artists.; Engravers.; Painters.; Printmakers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Minna Citron; estate of Minna Citron.
Additional exhibit catalogs, gift of Martha Paull, 2013.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Bookplate, bookplate of Louis N. Messing (Box 1)
  - Inventory (partial) of Minna Citron's paintings, graphics (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous, biographical sketches, photocopy of obituary, invitation to memorial service/celebration of life (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1940s; 1961-1965; 3 folders (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Photographs, personal (Box 1)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1932-1965; 1977,; 1985,; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, one-woman shows, 1930s-2010s; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, group shows, 1940s-1950s; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, group shows, 1960s; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Exhibition catalogs, undated (Box 2)
    - Exhibition catalogs, miscellaneous (Box 2)
      Gift of Martha H. Paull, 2013.
    - Exhibition posters (8) (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Publicity (Box 1)
  - Reviews, comments, 1937; 1946,; 1954 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts of essays, speeches (by title), 1947; 1949,; 1950,; 1963,; 1965,; undated; typescripts (Box 1)
  - Published articles, 1955; 1958, (Box 1)